<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Generated by Site-Server v6.0.0-08aa0e4b9d7d04f01a06489ce7063485f0bb69bc-1 (http://www.squarespace.com) on Thu, 26 Sep 2024 17:54:16 GMT
--><rss xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/" xmlns:itunes="http://www.itunes.com/dtds/podcast-1.0.dtd" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:media="http://www.rssboard.org/media-rss" version="2.0"><channel><title>Blog - Ryan C. Briggs</title><link>https://www.ryancbriggs.net/blog/</link><lastBuildDate>Tue, 02 Apr 2024 01:15:16 +0000</lastBuildDate><language>en-US</language><generator>Site-Server v6.0.0-08aa0e4b9d7d04f01a06489ce7063485f0bb69bc-1 (http://www.squarespace.com)</generator><description><![CDATA[]]></description><item><title>Reflections on a year of rowing</title><dc:creator>Ryan Briggs</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 02 Apr 2024 01:12:20 +0000</pubDate><link>https://www.ryancbriggs.net/blog/2024/4/1/reflections-on-a-year-of-rowing</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5acc1ee17e3c3a103525fb2b:5acd0d48562fa79982e73657:660b5b79900f3d6d32d4d8f1</guid><description><![CDATA[<p class="">I did my first indoor row on February 26, 2023. I rowed 1018 metres in 4 minutes and 30 seconds. I walk a decent amount and skate in the winter, but this was the start of my first serious exercise routine in about 20 years. Since then I have rowed 273 times and covered more than 1.3 million metres.</p><p class="">I started rowing after noticing my physical decline. I was approaching 40 and over the last few years I began to have back pain. I have fortunate genetics and typically don’t gain weight, but rather than getting chubby I was becoming weaker and slimmer. But it was the back problems—and fear of them growing worse—that finally scared me into trying to set up an exercise regime despite really hating exercise and not thinking of myself as an “exercise person.” </p><p class="">I thought about it for a bit and came up with 4 criteria for my future exercise regime:</p><ol data-rte-list="default"><li><p class="">It needed to be fully body, muscle and cardio</p></li><li><p class="">I would be unlikely to injure myself</p></li><li><p class="">I could get a good workout in 20 min</p></li><li><p class="">It would fit in my (small) basement</p></li></ol><p class="">I asked on Twitter and the replies quickly converged on either putting a pool in my basement (unlikely) or buying an erg. After borrowing a friend’s erg for a week, I settled on that and bought the <a href="https://shop.concept2.com/rowergs/298-model-d-with-pm5.html" target="_blank">standard C2 erg</a> that everyone seems to recommend. </p><h2>Sticking to it</h2><p class="">I’ve made half-hearted efforts at setting up an exercise habit before, but this was my first serious attempt.&nbsp; Rowing seemed pretty brutal and as I said I did not like exercise, so I wasn’t sure I’d stick to it. Here are 4 things that I did to try to help adherence:</p><ol data-rte-list="default"><li><p class="">I told everyone I was going to row regularly. This included talking about rowing a decent amount on social media. My goal here was to make it more embarrassing to fail.</p></li><li><p class="">I wrote a <a href="https://github.com/ryancbriggs/concept2-AH" target="_blank">series of R scripts</a> to visualize the rowing data from my erg and health data from my Apple Watch. I thought I’d find the health results motivating and I’d find the process rewarding because I like messing around with data. Rowing now wasn’t just exercise, it was adding a row to my dataset.</p></li><li><p class="">I used the data above to motivate myself. For example, I tracked my “cost per use of the erg.” One nice thing about this number is that it drops faster when your number of uses is lower (and so the habit isn’t as developed). I did not want to have just wasted like $1000 on exercise equipment I didn’t use, so seeing this number drop was motivating. Later, I started tracking my 5k and 2k times and found that motivating as well.</p></li><li><p class="">I found music that made rowing somewhat less terrible in the moment.</p></li></ol><h2>Results </h2><p class="">I have now been rowing for a little over a year and I have a pretty established exercise habit. I row at least a few times a week. On a heavy month I’ll do over 150k on the erg and on a light month I’ll do more like 75k. Here are a few of the things I’ve noticed about my body since rowing:</p><ul data-rte-list="default"><li><p class="">My posture got accidentally better after a few months. I noticed this when I realized I was looking at the things in my house from a slightly different angle. Everyone always says “remember to stand up straight” as advice to improve your posture but really they should be saying “build more muscle.”</p><ul data-rte-list="default"><li><p class="">Relatedly, I feel internally more solid in my core. This makes some ways I used to slouch kind of uncomfortable now.</p></li></ul></li><li><p class="">When I walk or stand I feel like I’m better connected to the ground. Almost like gravity is 10% greater, but without any associated strain. It took me like 6 to 8 months to notice this.</p></li><li><p class="">I eat way more, especially when I do longer rows. A 15k row runs a little over an hour for me and burns 900–1000 calories. When I’m doing longer rows I basically have to eat a second dinner, but I see this as a win because I like eating.</p></li><li><p class="">My resting heart rate is now about 20 bpm lower than when I started rowing.</p></li><li><p class="">I used to feel like my body was basically a homogenous solid. Now I feel like I have a skeleton with very specific muscles hanging off of it. I can use those specific muscles to do specific things. I sort of <em>feel</em> the specific muscles. This is a small positive, but it’s neat. It took me almost a year to notice this.</p></li><li><p class="">I’m 5-10 pounds heavier than when I started. My shirts fit tighter than before around my shoulders and my underwear fits tighter around my upper legs. I think my waist is actually a bit smaller, but I’m not totally sure as I didn’t take consistent measurements.</p></li><li><p class="">The back pain is gone.</p></li><li><p class="">Mental ticks that I associate with being younger are (sort of) back. If I do a row and then drive the car somewhere, I’m a more aggressive driver. A lot of things that I associate with having a “younger guy’s brain” are at least partially back. There are negatives here but on balance I like it.</p></li><li><p class="">It’s nice to be able to lift up your kids basically effortlessly, and run for a bit and feel fine.</p></li></ul><p class="">One thing that didn’t change is my daily energy level. My day to day mood feels basically the same as well, though rowing is a way that I can blow off steam when I’m grumpy. </p><p class="">After a few months of rowing I started channelling a lot of my natural competitive energy into beating my past rowing times. I think because of this I feel less competitive in other areas of life, like my job. I see this as a pure win because being competitive in science or academia is dumb as most of the actually important stuff is not zero sum and treating it as a competition tends to make people less happy.</p><p class="">Finally, I kind of love the harsh honesty of the erg. Unlike a lot of areas of life, it is just a zero bullshit environment. Your time is your time and if it’s slow then you should have gone harder. It reminds me of why I liked math instead of other subjects  when I was in grade school. There is a sort of austere clarity here.</p><p class="">Regular rowing has a few downsides too. On the negative side of the ledger:</p><ul data-rte-list="default"><li><p class="">Rowing takes time. I’ve spent over 95 hours rowing. Some of that would have been addictive phone time I wouldn’t miss, but some of it would have surely been put towards good stuff too. I think rowing is a pretty time-efficient form of exercise, but regularly exercising takes a lot of time.</p></li><li><p class="">I’m somewhat more vain now. I used to not really think about vanity, and when it did cross my mind I appreciated how I wasn’t vain at all. Now I think that’s not so impressive because I didn’t have anything to be vain about. I’m glad this discovery happened when I was already older.</p></li></ul><h2>My rowing performance</h2><p class="">This is the least important thing, but someone might want to know a bit about my rowing performance. My first row was a slow 1k. My next row was my first 2k, which I did in 9:08. I did my first 5k after a month of rowing and did it in 22:18. I’ve come pretty far, though of course many people row much faster. The table below shows my personal bests as of writing. My 2k is the weakest entry here because I hate that distance so <em>so</em> <strong>so</strong> much, but overall I’m pretty proud of my progress. Aside from these times, I also managed to row over 1 million metres in 2023 despite starting in late February. </p>





















  
  



<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="center">Event</th>
<th align="center">Time</th>
<th align="center">Pace</th>
<th align="center">Date</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody><tr>
<td align="center">2,000m</td>
<td align="center">7:32.7</td>
<td align="center">1:53.1</td>
<td align="center">06/24/23</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">5,000m</td>
<td align="center">19:54.9</td>
<td align="center">1:59.4</td>
<td align="center">12/12/23</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">6,000m</td>
<td align="center">24:40.1</td>
<td align="center">2:03.3</td>
<td align="center">09/17/23</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">10,000m</td>
<td align="center">41:42.1</td>
<td align="center">2:05.1</td>
<td align="center">03/02/24</td>
</tr>
</tbody></table>




  <p class="">Rowing still hurts and is kind of terrible though. At this point I don’t expect that will change.</p>]]></description></item><item><title>Development Studies programs should not shift their attention to the global rich</title><dc:creator>Ryan Briggs</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 20 Jul 2022 19:59:32 +0000</pubDate><link>https://www.ryancbriggs.net/blog/2022/7/20/development-studies-programs-should-not-shift-attention-to-the-global-rich</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5acc1ee17e3c3a103525fb2b:5acd0d48562fa79982e73657:62d8502ec59046277795a9ff</guid><description><![CDATA[<p class="">Many Development Studies programs, including <a href="https://gids.uoguelph.ca">mine</a>, are going through some soul searching about their place in academia and the broader international development ecosystem. This is due to a range of factors, but one major one is that a critical mass of people feel uneasy with the power dynamics involved in asserting that “we” in Development Studies (a “we” that lives in high income countries) study the problems of “them” (a “them” that lives in low or middle income countries). One can layer onto this base criticism a range of related ones, like those having to do with race for example.</p><p class="">One key question at stake here is “What should we be studying and teaching?” and one answer that is becoming increasingly common is that “development happens everywhere and so we should be studying and teaching about development problems that take place anywhere.” For example, in my institute our undergrads can <a href="https://gids.uoguelph.ca/future-students/international-development-studies-ba">pick 1 of 5 areas of emphasis</a> and one is “Development in the Canadian Context.”  I’m sympathetic to this view, and I know it comes from a good place, but I think it has a <strong>major</strong> blind spot. Here I’m going to first explain my agreement and then explain why despite this agreement I think orienting development studies programs towards the poor in rich countries is a bad idea. I’m writing about this publicly because I know at least a few other programs are having similar discussions and, frankly, I hope to influence them.</p><p class="">First, my agreement: I agree that “development happens everywhere,” or we at least hope that it does. I believe this because I’m fully on board with a Sen-style capabilities understanding of development. Development is about expanding people’s options to do things. This truly applies to everyone, everywhere. I also feel unease with many of the power dynamics involved in knowledge production in international development. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1093/afraf/adw009">I’ve written about this</a>.</p><p class="">Despite my unease and capability understanding of development: <strong>I think schools of Development Studies should remain focused mostly on things that help poorer people in low and middle income countries</strong>. To be very clear, this means that I think we should not study things that only help poorer people in high income countries. I’m all for studying how rich country policies, like migration or trade policies, affect the global poor, but I think the locus of our attention should be on ways to improve life for something like the bottom third of the world’s population. My reasoning is quite simple:</p><ol data-rte-list="default"><li><p class="">I think that all human lives should count equally</p></li><li><p class="">I think that the problems of those with the least are morally most pressing</p></li></ol><p class="">I think most Development Studies scholars agree with me on these points. Aside from having lots of personal anecdotes, when I <a href="https://forum.effectivealtruism.org/posts/xqBevMwS8v5adMdKm/results-of-a-survey-of-international-development-professors">recently did a survey of this community</a>, almost 80% of the people surveyed agreed or strongly agreed that “From a moral perspective, people should care about the well-being of all human beings on the planet equally; they should not favour the well-being of people who are especially close to them either physically or emotionally.” Points 1 and 2 lead me to think that everyone has—but academics in Development Studies in particular have—an obligation to work on problems that affect the worst off people regardless of where they live<em>.</em></p><p class="">The final step in the argument then is a simple empirical point: <strong>the vast majority of poor people in rich countries are not globally poor</strong>. In fact, they are globally well off. This may be surprising to many people, but it’s quite clearly true when looking at any population aggregate. Of course one can find a single person somewhere in the United States or Canada that is worse off than, say, the average of the bottom decile in Malawi, but one cannot find very many people like this. For example, look at the graph below that I made using <a href="https://pip.worldbank.org">povcalnet</a> data (and <a href="https://cepr.net/milanovic-on-international-inequality/">credit to Branko Milanovic</a> for this style of graph).</p>





















  
  














































  

    
  
    

      

      
        <figure class="
              sqs-block-image-figure
              intrinsic
            "
        >
          
        
        

        
          
            
          
            
                
                
                
                
                
                
                
                <img data-stretch="false" data-image="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5acc1ee17e3c3a103525fb2b/d2233c02-1eda-4ad4-b776-bb655a09f909/Mil_graph.png" data-image-dimensions="2400x1800" data-image-focal-point="0.5,0.5" alt="" data-load="false" elementtiming="system-image-block" src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5acc1ee17e3c3a103525fb2b/d2233c02-1eda-4ad4-b776-bb655a09f909/Mil_graph.png?format=1000w" width="2400" height="1800" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, (max-width: 767px) 100vw, 100vw" onload="this.classList.add(&quot;loaded&quot;)" srcset="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5acc1ee17e3c3a103525fb2b/d2233c02-1eda-4ad4-b776-bb655a09f909/Mil_graph.png?format=100w 100w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5acc1ee17e3c3a103525fb2b/d2233c02-1eda-4ad4-b776-bb655a09f909/Mil_graph.png?format=300w 300w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5acc1ee17e3c3a103525fb2b/d2233c02-1eda-4ad4-b776-bb655a09f909/Mil_graph.png?format=500w 500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5acc1ee17e3c3a103525fb2b/d2233c02-1eda-4ad4-b776-bb655a09f909/Mil_graph.png?format=750w 750w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5acc1ee17e3c3a103525fb2b/d2233c02-1eda-4ad4-b776-bb655a09f909/Mil_graph.png?format=1000w 1000w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5acc1ee17e3c3a103525fb2b/d2233c02-1eda-4ad4-b776-bb655a09f909/Mil_graph.png?format=1500w 1500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5acc1ee17e3c3a103525fb2b/d2233c02-1eda-4ad4-b776-bb655a09f909/Mil_graph.png?format=2500w 2500w" loading="lazy" decoding="async" data-loader="sqs">

            
          
        
          
        

        
      
        </figure>
      

    
  


  





  <p class="">The graph is showing average income or consumption in dollars per year (left axis) or day (right axis) for each decile in the population of 6 countries (note the axes are logged). One straightforward reading from this graph is that the poorest 10% in Canada (on average) earn more than the richest 10% in Malawi (on average). But the inequality is larger still, because the richer country surveys measure poverty using <em>income</em> while LIC surveys typically measure poverty using dollars of <em>consumption</em>. <a href="https://www.vox.com/the-big-idea/2018/2/1/16959634/millions-americans-destitute-2-day-worlds-poorest-deaton-aid">I’ve discussed this issue before</a>, but the crux of it is that when people in Canada report having zero <em>income </em>they typically have positive consumption (e.g. health insurance, food from food banks, room in a shelter). So the graph is overstating how badly off the poorest Canadians are, and even with that overstatement we are globally privileged. To be utterly clear: Canada can and should do better on poverty in Canada, but that isn’t the question at stake here. The question at stake here is whether the poor in Canada are comparable in size or deprivation to the poor elsewhere in the world, and the answer is clearly no.</p><p class="">For this reason, I think that the only way to defend re-orienting Development Studies towards problems of the poor in, say, Canada is to assert that Canadian lives are morally worth more than non-Canadian lives. Worse, the multiple has to be very large. <strong>Even if you feel that Canadian lives are worth 100x more than the lives of others, about 99% of people living under $2 a day would still live in other countries</strong> (<a href="https://ryanbriggs.shinyapps.io/PovcalNet_weighted/">I made a simulation so you can see how this works for yourself</a>, more discussion <a href="https://www.ryancbriggs.net/blog">here</a>).</p><p class="">I understand that Development Studies programs are in a weird position right now, but I really hope that the brutal level of inequality across countries continues to enrage us enough to clarify our focus. The vast majority of deprivation in the world exists in low and middle income countries and, morally, this is where our attention ought to stay.</p>]]></description></item><item><title>Global poverty trends with national discounting</title><dc:creator>Ryan Briggs</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 31 May 2021 18:02:53 +0000</pubDate><link>https://www.ryancbriggs.net/blog/2021/5/31/global-poverty-trends-with-national-discounting</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5acc1ee17e3c3a103525fb2b:5acd0d48562fa79982e73657:60b520d702da6a64526ed9d4</guid><description><![CDATA[<p class="">Every Fall I teach a third-year undergraduate course on Poverty &amp; Inequality at the University of Guelph. The first third of the course is on normative issues and some history, the second third is all about measurement, and the final third is about the “science” of poverty, or what we know about what poverty causes and what can cause poverty to go up or down.</p><p class="">In the two first sections of the course we sometimes discuss issues of nationalism. What do we owe to people in our country vs. people elsewhere? How should we feel about using different (PPP) poverty lines in different places? Just descriptively, how much poverty exists within Canada (or the United States) relative to other countries?</p><p class="">I made <a href="https://ryanbriggs.shinyapps.io/PovcalNet_weighted/">the following Shiny app</a> in order to let my students explore these and other related questions on their own. The app uses data from <a href="http://iresearch.worldbank.org/PovcalNet/home.aspx">povcalnet</a> and lets you select a home country, a poverty line, and it lets you move a slider to decide how much you value the life of a foreigner relative to the life of someone in your home country. It will then show you a “weighted global poverty” headcount ratio, where the global population has been adjusted to take your weighting into account. When you load it, it looks like this:</p>


































































  

    
  
    

      

      
        <figure class="
              sqs-block-image-figure
              intrinsic
            "
        >
          
        
        

        
          
            
          
            
                
                
                
                
                
                
                
                <img data-stretch="false" data-image="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5acc1ee17e3c3a103525fb2b/1622483523281-6YN7KMSXFSQVRM6QMUAB/Screen+Shot+2021-05-31+at+1.46.19+PM.png" data-image-dimensions="1832x844" data-image-focal-point="0.5,0.5" alt="" data-load="false" elementtiming="system-image-block" src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5acc1ee17e3c3a103525fb2b/1622483523281-6YN7KMSXFSQVRM6QMUAB/Screen+Shot+2021-05-31+at+1.46.19+PM.png?format=1000w" width="1832" height="844" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, (max-width: 767px) 100vw, 100vw" onload="this.classList.add(&quot;loaded&quot;)" srcset="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5acc1ee17e3c3a103525fb2b/1622483523281-6YN7KMSXFSQVRM6QMUAB/Screen+Shot+2021-05-31+at+1.46.19+PM.png?format=100w 100w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5acc1ee17e3c3a103525fb2b/1622483523281-6YN7KMSXFSQVRM6QMUAB/Screen+Shot+2021-05-31+at+1.46.19+PM.png?format=300w 300w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5acc1ee17e3c3a103525fb2b/1622483523281-6YN7KMSXFSQVRM6QMUAB/Screen+Shot+2021-05-31+at+1.46.19+PM.png?format=500w 500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5acc1ee17e3c3a103525fb2b/1622483523281-6YN7KMSXFSQVRM6QMUAB/Screen+Shot+2021-05-31+at+1.46.19+PM.png?format=750w 750w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5acc1ee17e3c3a103525fb2b/1622483523281-6YN7KMSXFSQVRM6QMUAB/Screen+Shot+2021-05-31+at+1.46.19+PM.png?format=1000w 1000w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5acc1ee17e3c3a103525fb2b/1622483523281-6YN7KMSXFSQVRM6QMUAB/Screen+Shot+2021-05-31+at+1.46.19+PM.png?format=1500w 1500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5acc1ee17e3c3a103525fb2b/1622483523281-6YN7KMSXFSQVRM6QMUAB/Screen+Shot+2021-05-31+at+1.46.19+PM.png?format=2500w 2500w" loading="lazy" decoding="async" data-loader="sqs">

            
          
        
          
        

        
      
        </figure>
      

    
  


  





  <p class="">China is huge and used to be very poor, so even if we count everyone the same then China still accounted for a lot of the global population living under $2/day in 1980 (I’m always going to be using 2011 PPPs). Canada is small and well off, so even if we say that a foreigner’s life counts for only 1% of a Canadian’s life and we set the poverty line at $40/day, most poverty would still be outside Canada.</p>


































































  

    
  
    

      

      
        <figure class="
              sqs-block-image-figure
              intrinsic
            "
        >
          
        
        

        
          
            
          
            
                
                
                
                
                
                
                
                <img data-stretch="false" data-image="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5acc1ee17e3c3a103525fb2b/1622483790820-MWX84OX2GOE3VYBUF5MD/Screen+Shot+2021-05-31+at+1.46.46+PM.png" data-image-dimensions="1818x834" data-image-focal-point="0.5,0.5" alt="" data-load="false" elementtiming="system-image-block" src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5acc1ee17e3c3a103525fb2b/1622483790820-MWX84OX2GOE3VYBUF5MD/Screen+Shot+2021-05-31+at+1.46.46+PM.png?format=1000w" width="1818" height="834" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, (max-width: 767px) 100vw, 100vw" onload="this.classList.add(&quot;loaded&quot;)" srcset="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5acc1ee17e3c3a103525fb2b/1622483790820-MWX84OX2GOE3VYBUF5MD/Screen+Shot+2021-05-31+at+1.46.46+PM.png?format=100w 100w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5acc1ee17e3c3a103525fb2b/1622483790820-MWX84OX2GOE3VYBUF5MD/Screen+Shot+2021-05-31+at+1.46.46+PM.png?format=300w 300w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5acc1ee17e3c3a103525fb2b/1622483790820-MWX84OX2GOE3VYBUF5MD/Screen+Shot+2021-05-31+at+1.46.46+PM.png?format=500w 500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5acc1ee17e3c3a103525fb2b/1622483790820-MWX84OX2GOE3VYBUF5MD/Screen+Shot+2021-05-31+at+1.46.46+PM.png?format=750w 750w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5acc1ee17e3c3a103525fb2b/1622483790820-MWX84OX2GOE3VYBUF5MD/Screen+Shot+2021-05-31+at+1.46.46+PM.png?format=1000w 1000w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5acc1ee17e3c3a103525fb2b/1622483790820-MWX84OX2GOE3VYBUF5MD/Screen+Shot+2021-05-31+at+1.46.46+PM.png?format=1500w 1500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5acc1ee17e3c3a103525fb2b/1622483790820-MWX84OX2GOE3VYBUF5MD/Screen+Shot+2021-05-31+at+1.46.46+PM.png?format=2500w 2500w" loading="lazy" decoding="async" data-loader="sqs">

            
          
        
          
        

        
      
        </figure>
      

    
  


  





  <p class="">Finally, one nice thing is that if you set the slider to zero then you can see changes in headcount ratios over time and under any line for any country. The following graph shows how the % of the Canadian population living under $40/day has changed over time.</p>


































































  

    
  
    

      

      
        <figure class="
              sqs-block-image-figure
              intrinsic
            "
        >
          
        
        

        
          
            
          
            
                
                
                
                
                
                
                
                <img data-stretch="false" data-image="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5acc1ee17e3c3a103525fb2b/1622483889805-SGGE39L2I4HWAQ6DIJNS/Screen+Shot+2021-05-31+at+1.47.02+PM.png" data-image-dimensions="1828x834" data-image-focal-point="0.5,0.5" alt="" data-load="false" elementtiming="system-image-block" src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5acc1ee17e3c3a103525fb2b/1622483889805-SGGE39L2I4HWAQ6DIJNS/Screen+Shot+2021-05-31+at+1.47.02+PM.png?format=1000w" width="1828" height="834" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, (max-width: 767px) 100vw, 100vw" onload="this.classList.add(&quot;loaded&quot;)" srcset="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5acc1ee17e3c3a103525fb2b/1622483889805-SGGE39L2I4HWAQ6DIJNS/Screen+Shot+2021-05-31+at+1.47.02+PM.png?format=100w 100w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5acc1ee17e3c3a103525fb2b/1622483889805-SGGE39L2I4HWAQ6DIJNS/Screen+Shot+2021-05-31+at+1.47.02+PM.png?format=300w 300w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5acc1ee17e3c3a103525fb2b/1622483889805-SGGE39L2I4HWAQ6DIJNS/Screen+Shot+2021-05-31+at+1.47.02+PM.png?format=500w 500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5acc1ee17e3c3a103525fb2b/1622483889805-SGGE39L2I4HWAQ6DIJNS/Screen+Shot+2021-05-31+at+1.47.02+PM.png?format=750w 750w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5acc1ee17e3c3a103525fb2b/1622483889805-SGGE39L2I4HWAQ6DIJNS/Screen+Shot+2021-05-31+at+1.47.02+PM.png?format=1000w 1000w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5acc1ee17e3c3a103525fb2b/1622483889805-SGGE39L2I4HWAQ6DIJNS/Screen+Shot+2021-05-31+at+1.47.02+PM.png?format=1500w 1500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5acc1ee17e3c3a103525fb2b/1622483889805-SGGE39L2I4HWAQ6DIJNS/Screen+Shot+2021-05-31+at+1.47.02+PM.png?format=2500w 2500w" loading="lazy" decoding="async" data-loader="sqs">

            
          
        
          
        

        
      
        </figure>
      

    
  


  





  <p class=""><a href="https://ryanbriggs.shinyapps.io/PovcalNet_weighted/">Once I built this I thought that possibly other people would find it useful too, so I posted it on shinyapps so anyone could use it.</a> I think it offers a nice way to get students to think about some of the normative issues and measurement issues at work when we talk about “global poverty.”</p>]]></description></item><item><title>The Academic Job Market in Canada</title><dc:creator>Ryan Briggs</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 19 Feb 2021 15:51:22 +0000</pubDate><link>https://www.ryancbriggs.net/blog/2021/2/19/the-academic-job-market-in-canada</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5acc1ee17e3c3a103525fb2b:5acd0d48562fa79982e73657:602fd511c9160e1ba97722e0</guid><description><![CDATA[<p class="">Since moving back to Canada, a number of Americans have asked me for advice on the Canadian academic job market. After doing this a few times I realized: 1. it would be easier to answer these questions once and just point people to the answers, and 2. there is probably enough demand for this that a public document would be useful. </p><p class="">For anyone wondering if I’m qualified to answer these questions or wondering about my biases: I’m a Canadian who did grad school (political science) in the US and got a VAP (2013) and then a TT job (2014) in the US and then in 2018 got a TT job in Canada and moved back to Canada. I’ve applied to lots of jobs in Canada and the US, been involved in hiring processes, seen flyouts in both countries, etc.. </p><p class="">My most important academic job market advice is that <strong>a large portion of the variation in the outcome is</strong>, while not literally random,<strong> totally out of your control</strong>. Remember that the job market is a matching process and, while you can do some things to make yourself more likely to get a job in general, you cannot control the other side of that process. We’ve all seen attractive people who don’t get a second date because of “fit.” The academic job market has this dynamic. TT jobs are not statements about your merit or academic contribution or personal self-worth. They’re the outcome of a matching process.</p><p class="">With that said, here are my answers to the most common questions that people ask me about academic jobs in Canada:</p><p class=""><em>Do I want a job in Canada?</em></p><p class="">I don’t know, maybe? It is a different country and a lot of cultural norms and institutions are different, plus in much of Canada the weather is bad (think of the weather in each contiguous US state). Median or 10th percentile academic salaries are very good compared to the US and most faculty have strong unions, but 90th percentile salaries are not so good and the dollar is generally weak and cost of living in major cities is high. The vibe of the job is more relaxed than in American academia, which has pros and cons. If this is your main question, talk to people who moved and ask them about it. <a href="http://twitter.com/ryancbriggs/with_replies">I’m available here</a>.</p><p data-rte-preserve-empty="true" class=""></p><p class=""><em>Where can I find Canadian jobs?</em></p><p class="">“Normal” American places like <a href="https://www.apsanet.org/eJobs">APSA ejobs</a> or <a href="https://www.isanet.org/Professional-Resources/Employment/Jobs">ISA’s job listing</a> have a subset of all Canadian jobs. In my experience <a href="https://www.universityaffairs.ca/search-job/">University Affairs</a> was the best single place to look for jobs, even though their search function is horrible. You can also subscribe to discipline-specific mailing lists like <a href="https://polcan2.ca/polcan.php">POLCAN2</a>, and in exchange for sending you very long and mostly useless emails you will also get a listing of jobs.</p><p data-rte-preserve-empty="true" class=""></p><p class=""><em>How many jobs are there?</em></p><p class="">Not that many. Canada has around the population of California, so scale your expectations accordingly. For Americans, I’d say think of Canada as adding a few jobs a year to your pool of possibilities.</p><p data-rte-preserve-empty="true" class=""></p><p class=""><em>In the job market, is there a preference for quantitative methods?</em></p><p class="">No. If anything, it cuts the other way. Most people in most Canadian political science departments do qualitative work. There is probably a little bit of junior-senior variation here, and probably our “top 3” schools (Toronto, McGill, UBC) lean more quantitative than do the others (in general these schools face a little more towards American academia than do our other universities), but most people do qualitative work. Job calls will often specify this though, so you can always pick and choose (it’s a matching process!) and if nothing around methods is listed in the job ad then I would apply regardless of the kind of work you do.</p><p data-rte-preserve-empty="true" class=""></p><p class=""><em>Do you need a publication in a top journal to get a job?</em></p><p class="">No, but they always help. Even in departments that insist they do not care about rankings (“the rankings are US-centric anyways”) and where the professors rarely publish in APSR or IO or whatever, they still help. But they’re not necessary. My mental model here is that you want credible signals that you’re amazing. You can get that with: a “top” journal article, a prestigious post-doc, a prestigious grant or a lot of grant money, a letter from someone impressive, etc.. But again: it’s a matching process not a reward or a statement of merit.</p><p data-rte-preserve-empty="true" class=""></p><p class=""><em>What is the role of networking in Canadian job market for political science positions?</em></p><p class="">I think it’s important, especially if you’re coming from the US. My best advice (what I did) was to find profs from Canadian schools at US conferences and get coffee with them. <strong>I’d love if Canadian profs could send me more advice on this point as I don’t know what else to tell people.</strong></p><p data-rte-preserve-empty="true" class=""></p><p class=""><em>The job ad says Canadians are favoured. Is this true?</em></p><p class="">This varies by institution. I think most places are looking for the best candidate regardless of nationality, but I’ve heard of one department that strongly prioritizes Canadians. Networking can help you know how seriously departments take this. If you don’t know, I think you can probably assume they don’t take it seriously and will just try to hire the candidate they think is best.</p><p class="">A somewhat similar issue is that sometimes people claim that Americans either won’t come if they get the job or won’t stay (winter). I’m not sure if these claims are genuine or just deployed to promote some candidates over others, but regardless you can and should tailor you application to explain why you want to come to Canada. Did you do grad school in Michigan? Tell us you loved the weather. Do you have family in Toronto? Tell us. Networking helps here too.</p><p data-rte-preserve-empty="true" class=""></p>]]></description></item><item><title>Isaac is a lucky boy</title><dc:creator>Ryan Briggs</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 01 Oct 2015 23:20:00 +0000</pubDate><link>https://www.ryancbriggs.net/blog/2015/10/1/isaac-is-a-lucky-boy</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5acc1ee17e3c3a103525fb2b:5acd0d48562fa79982e73657:5acd0d5eaa4a998f3fbc7077</guid><description><![CDATA[<p>About two weeks ago, my first child, Isaac was born. We spent a standard two days in the hospital and then went home. After about 5 hours at home, in his third day of life, Isaac developed a fever of 103 and we went straight to the ER. After a few days of tests, we learned that Isaac’s blood and kidneys were infected with <a target="_blank" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Enterococcus">enterococcus</a>&nbsp;and that he probably had bacterial <a target="_blank" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neonatal_meningitis">meningitis</a>. This kind of thing is incredibly uncommon and no one really knows how he got infected. He was just incredibly unlucky…</p><p>…except that he really wasn’t.</p><p>For four years now, I’ve been teaching international development. One of my first questions to my students is: “If you knew nothing about yourself (e.g. gender, race) or where you would be born,&nbsp;<em>when</em>&nbsp;would you like to be born?” (I think I got this question originally from Angus Deaton?) The students can choose any time from the dawn of humanity to the present day. After a bit of thought, students quickly converge on “now” as the right answer. I like to stress to them that “now” is the right answer not only because the world is wealthier and more people have iPhones. Women are treated far better today than at any time in the past, more people have political freedoms today, and <strong>far</strong>&nbsp;fewer children die.&nbsp;</p><p>That final point felt important but abstract until a few weeks ago. Child mortality feels incredibly real now. Thankfully, in being born <strong>now </strong>and <strong>in America</strong>, Isaac is damn lucky. By just about any comparison,&nbsp;<a target="_blank" href="https://ourworldindata.org/child-mortality">child mortality is the US is very low</a>. It’s about ten times lower than much poorer countries like Malawi, and it’s also about ten times lower in America today than in the 1940s. Presently,&nbsp;<a target="_blank" href="https://www.cdc.gov/meningitis/bacterial.html">about 10% of children in America with bacterial meningitis die</a>. In the 1970s,&nbsp;<a target="_blank" href="https://emedicine.medscape.com/article/1176960-overview#a7">the rate was about 50%</a>.</p>


































































  

    
  
    

      

      
        <figure class="
              sqs-block-image-figure
              intrinsic
            "
        >
          
        
        

        
          
            
          
            
                
                
                
                
                
                
                
                <img data-stretch="false" data-image="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5acc1ee17e3c3a103525fb2b/1523387983174-XM2F2CU0PTFYZH5FMSS7/tumblr_inline_nvk1re5Ltc1qz7mwz_500.jpg" data-image-dimensions="500x667" data-image-focal-point="0.5,0.5" alt="" data-load="false" elementtiming="system-image-block" src="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5acc1ee17e3c3a103525fb2b/1523387983174-XM2F2CU0PTFYZH5FMSS7/tumblr_inline_nvk1re5Ltc1qz7mwz_500.jpg?format=1000w" width="500" height="667" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, (max-width: 767px) 100vw, 100vw" onload="this.classList.add(&quot;loaded&quot;)" srcset="https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5acc1ee17e3c3a103525fb2b/1523387983174-XM2F2CU0PTFYZH5FMSS7/tumblr_inline_nvk1re5Ltc1qz7mwz_500.jpg?format=100w 100w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5acc1ee17e3c3a103525fb2b/1523387983174-XM2F2CU0PTFYZH5FMSS7/tumblr_inline_nvk1re5Ltc1qz7mwz_500.jpg?format=300w 300w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5acc1ee17e3c3a103525fb2b/1523387983174-XM2F2CU0PTFYZH5FMSS7/tumblr_inline_nvk1re5Ltc1qz7mwz_500.jpg?format=500w 500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5acc1ee17e3c3a103525fb2b/1523387983174-XM2F2CU0PTFYZH5FMSS7/tumblr_inline_nvk1re5Ltc1qz7mwz_500.jpg?format=750w 750w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5acc1ee17e3c3a103525fb2b/1523387983174-XM2F2CU0PTFYZH5FMSS7/tumblr_inline_nvk1re5Ltc1qz7mwz_500.jpg?format=1000w 1000w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5acc1ee17e3c3a103525fb2b/1523387983174-XM2F2CU0PTFYZH5FMSS7/tumblr_inline_nvk1re5Ltc1qz7mwz_500.jpg?format=1500w 1500w, https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5acc1ee17e3c3a103525fb2b/1523387983174-XM2F2CU0PTFYZH5FMSS7/tumblr_inline_nvk1re5Ltc1qz7mwz_500.jpg?format=2500w 2500w" loading="lazy" decoding="async" data-loader="sqs">

            
          
        
          
        

        
      
        </figure>
      

    
  


  





  <p>Isaac is doing well. He is 13 days into a 21 day course of antibiotics and in his 16th day of life. He is eating well, he is above his birth weight, he has had no seizures, he has no signs of cranial inflammation, and he is doing regular baby stuff.&nbsp;&nbsp;He is expected to make a complete recovery. Untreated, he would have almost certainly died. He is damn lucky to have been born now in America.</p><p>I’ve known these statistics (well, aside from the ones on meningitis) for some time, but they carry a lot more emotional weight now. Most babies in Isaac’s situation still die. Development is the process of making that not so.</p><p> </p><p>PS</p><p>Meningitis is pretty rare, so if the thought of babies dying moves you then probably the best thing you can do at the moment is to <a target="_blank" href="https://www.givewell.org/charities/amf">donate to the Against Malaria Foundation</a>. Giving out insecticide-treated bed nets is one of the most reliable ways of reducing child mortality.</p><p>PPS (April 3, 2016)</p><p>At about 6 ½ months old, Isaac is doing very well. He is at or above average on pretty much everything that we can measure. His first month of life was terrifying for us, but he really was incredibly lucky. Thanks to everyone for the well wishes.</p><p> </p>]]></description></item><item><title>The Drunk World Bank Twitterbot</title><dc:creator>Ryan Briggs</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 24 Mar 2015 20:36:00 +0000</pubDate><link>https://www.ryancbriggs.net/blog/2015/3/24/the-drunk-world-bank-twitterbot</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5acc1ee17e3c3a103525fb2b:5acd0d48562fa79982e73657:5acd11c20e2e72f4e517daaa</guid><description><![CDATA[<p><a target="_blank" href="https://twitter.com/DrunkWB">I made a twitterbot</a>&nbsp;that posts pseudo-random tweets formed from samples of text from the five most recent <a target="_blank" href="https://openknowledge.worldbank.org/handle/10986/2124">World Development Reports</a>. My reasons for writing the bot, in order of importance, were: I wanted to learn something new in R, I thought that the results would make me laugh, I had a little bit of time to kill at ORD after the <a target="_blank" href="http://www.mpsanet.org">MPSA conference</a>, and finally, I thought that the resulting development babble might make us think a little about how development experts communicate. Here is one example tweet:</p>























<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">It recognized that legal equality was not revealed as shown by the expansion of the variation in crime rates in agrarian economies.</p>— Drunk World Bank (@DrunkWB) <a href="https://twitter.com/DrunkWB/status/591618513971851264?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">April 24, 2015</a></blockquote>



  <h2>The Problem</h2><p>My goal in writing the bot was to produce text that was recognizably from a development agency like the Bank but was also random enough to be funny. It had to have enough syntactical structure to sort of make sense, but it had to reach this point without any actual knowledge of grammar. This is a perfect application of Markov chains, and this entire project was inspired by <a target="_blank" href="http://partiallyderivative.com/news/2015/4/17/episode-20-dont-let-baseball-ruin-statistics">episode 20 of Partially Derivative</a>&nbsp;when Chris and Jonathan were talking about <a target="_blank" href="https://twitter.com/BeerSnobSays">drunk beer reviews</a>. As I write this, I realize that I must have lifted the idea of calling the bot “drunk”&nbsp;from <a target="_blank" href="https://twitter.com/gjreda">Greg Reda</a>, so hat tip to Greg.</p><p>I read <a target="_blank" href="http://www.gregreda.com/2015/03/30/beer-review-markov-chains/">Greg’s excellent post on Markov chains</a>&nbsp;and the <a target="_blank" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Markov_chain">Markov chain wikipedia page</a>&nbsp;and then googled around to find someone who had made a similar bot in R (most are in Python). I couldn’t find a Markov chain twitterbot written in R, but I did find <a target="_blank" href="http://www.seangrah.am/programming/listen-up-you-odiferous-rumpfed-scullian-aka-programming-a-funny-twitterbot-in-r/">a blog post that gave me useful sample code</a>&nbsp;for posting text from R to twitter. Aside from these sources, it seemed that I had to solve the problem myself.</p><h2>My Approach</h2><p>I had no real experience with Markov chains before this project, and at first they sounded complicated. However, like a lot of mathematical ideas, they are remarkably simple once you get them. The fundamental idea is that we can make a chain of predictions where each prediction for the next turn (t+1) is informed only by information present in the current state (t). In my case, I knew that I wanted to chain together words that had local structure so that any set of three consecutive words would make sense. I also wanted to do this based on the language of the Bank, so I started by copying and pasting all of the text (excluding bibliographies and boilerplate text) from the five most recent World Development Reports into a plain text file. I then cut this text file into all consecutive three word segments (word triplets) and counted the frequency with which they occurred in the text. Most occurred once, but some were more common.</p><p>To start the chain I draw one word triplet randomly, but with the probability of being selected being proportional to the triplet’s use in the WDRs. That three word triplet is the start of our tweet. Perhaps it is “Tailor technology to”. Next,&nbsp;find the subset of all word triplets whose first two words are the same as the last two words of the current tweet (technology to). In the current example, that set is small and includes only “technology to democratize”,&nbsp;“technology to local”, and “technology to make”. I then draw another tweet at random (but using the probability weights) from this subset and add the last word onto the current tweet. Perhaps it now reads “Tailor technology to democratize”. This process is repeated until you have a string that is long enough to be a tweet. In this way, we can build up a tweet where each additional word is selected only using information on the two trailing words. The result is the local structure that makes most tweets at least partially intelligble.</p><p>I’m leaving out a lot of details like: cleaning the WDR text to avoid things like page numbers, inset boxes of text, or tables; little tweaks to get the tweet to be the right length or avoid word repetition; or how I scheduled the posting to twitter; but that is the general idea.</p><h2>Improving my approach</h2><p>The naive approach above worked, but the tweets felt too random. Reading them, I could see that part of the problem was with the start and end of tweets. Tweets ending in words like “and” seemed off. My first solution was to include a list of words that would be cut from tweets before posting, but this was a hack and the list of “bad ending words” kept growing.</p><p>I realized that a much better solution was to scan the WDR text and isolate the word triplets that start or end sentences. I could then use those triplets as bookends for the rest of the chain. Finding these starting or ending triplets is a fairly simple problem, as the start of English sentences have capital letters that follow a period and a space, and all sentences end in a period and a space. After some pattern matching, I produced three tables of word triplets. One had the word triplets that start sentences and their frequencies, one had the middle words and their frequencies, and one had sentence ending words. I then worked these new tables into the matching procedure above. I would start with a draw from the starting triplets file and then fill it out with the middle words before capping it with a draw from the ending words table. I’m rather proud of the results:</p>























<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Formal arrangements to share information on disaster response can worsen it.</p>— Drunk World Bank (@DrunkWB) <a href="https://twitter.com/DrunkWB/status/591330088009932801?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">April 23, 2015</a></blockquote>]]></description></item></channel></rss>